Library of Social and Economic Aspects of Medicine of Michael M. Davis,
Library of Social and Economic Aspects of Medicine of Michael M. Davis
1920-1966
Davis, Michael Marks, 1879-1971
60 linear feet; ca. 400,000 items
Mss.arc
New York Academy of Medicine Library. Rare Book Room.
Biographical Note
Michael Marks Davis was a medical economist and advocate for comprehensive medical care and national health insurance. He was born on November 19, 1879, in New York City. He attended City College and later Columbia University, where he studied economics and sociology under Franklin H. Giddings and received his PhD in 1906.
In 1905, he joined the staff of the People’s Institute at Cooper Union, where he worked in social settlements. Davis then began his career in the health field as the director of the Boston Dispensary, a position he held from 1910 to 1920. At the Dispensary, he introduced the concept of a pay clinic, which allowed patients of modest means to pay a small fee for services.
In 1920, he was recruited by the Rockefeller Foundation to conduct a seven-year project introducing new forms of ambulatory care to hospitals and dispensaries in New York City. During this period, Davis was also active in the Committee on the Cost of Medical Care. In 1928, he became the director of medical services at the Julius Rosenwald Fund. While there, he promoted the concept of pay clinics that he had developed while at the Boston Dispensary. His department also gave assistance to the research leading to the establishment of the Blue Cross system.
In 1936, with support from the Rosenwald Fund, Davis established the Committee for Research in Medical Economics, which he directed until 1951. The Committee funded studies and published Medical Care, the first periodical in the United States devoted to the economic and social aspects of health services, from 1941 to 1944.
Davis contributed to health legislation throughout his career. In 1934-1935, helped draft the Social Security Act and contributed to Senator Robert F. Wagner’s efforts towards health care reform. In 1945, he helped President Harry S. Truman draft a message supporting a national health program. The following year Davis founded the Committee for the Nation’s Health, which promoted national health insurance.
Throughout his life Davis was a prolific writer. He wrote 12 books and over 250 articles. His last book, Medical Care for Tomorrow, was published in 1956.
Dr. Davis was married to Janet Haynes from 1907 until her death in 1950. They had three sons: Paul, Burnet, and Michael M., Jr. Davis married Alice Taylor in 1951. Dr. Davis died on August 19, 1971.
Sources:
Michael M. Davis: A Tribute. Compiled by Alice Taylor Davis. Chicago: Center for Health Administration Studies, University of Chicago, [1972].
Mullner, Ross M. “Davis, Michael M.” In: Mullner, Ross M., ed. Encyclopedia of Health Services Research. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage, 2009. Retrieved from: http://books.google.com/
Rosen, George. “Michael M. Davis (November 19, 1879-August 19, 1971): Pioneer in Medical Care.” American Journal of Public Health. Vol. 62, No. 3, 1972: 321-323. Retrieved from: http://ajph.aphapublications.org/
Scope and Content
A collection of over 400,000 pieces related to the legislation, organization, and economics of government-sponsored public medical care in the United States. The files include correspondence, confidential reports, special surveys, pamphlets, documents, clippings and ephemera spanning the years 1920-1966.
Arrangement
The original order of the collection has been maintained. The collection is organized into six series:
Medical Economics and Medical Sociology
Medical Care in the United States
Legislation and Legal Aspects
Organizations
Medical Care in Foreign Countries
Personalities
Alternate Form of Material
Microfilm copy of the Committee for the Nation's Health Records are available at the National Library of Medicine.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of The New York Academy of Medicine Library. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Health service administrators -- United States.; Medical economics -- United States.; Health insurance -- United States.; Social medicine -- United States.; Legislation, medical -- United States.; Health care reform; American Medical Association.; Committee for the Nation’s Health; Committee on the Cost of Medical Care; Davis, Michael Marks, 1879-1971
Container List
- Medical Economics and Medical Sociology, Series 1
  Arrangement
  Divided into nineteen sub-series, each futher sub-divided into subject-catalogued folders.
  Scope and Content
  This series contains material that is concerned with the cost of medical care and with special studies by, for, and about the Committee on the Costs of Medical Care, including confidential reports in typescript carbon copies by such eminent authorities of the 1930s as Haven Emerson, Louis I. Reed, and C. Rufus Rorem. A great deal of the work concerns Michael M. Davis' evaluations of the work of this important committee and its implications for the development of its recommendations, made during the period of Davis' term as director of Medical Services of the Julius Rosenwald Fund during the depths of the depression, when the health needs of the population were in great flow and public resources at their lowest ebb. The files are filled with publications, special studies, reports, drafts of minutes of committee meetings, and special groups concerned with public income data, taxes, and similar material (with much of a contemporary and ephemeral nature) concerning President Franklin D. Roosevelt's Committee on Economic Security and the Advisory Council on Economic Security, from the time of its establishment by executive order on June 29, 1934. This is supplemented by special studies (some undertaken by Dr. Davis or his associates) on the program of grants-in-aid for rural hospital services, and of Social Security programs. Many special stuides, both published and unpublished, are in this group of files, such as those on the attitudes of Roman Catholics toward Social Security, the report of the Michigan Governor's Study Commission on Prepaid Hospital and Medical Care Plans (1962), etc.
  Original questionnaires returned by certain labor unions, requresting information on their attitudes toward and experience with medical care and hospital insurance, are in one of these drawers, along with manuscript reports, typescripts of articles, addresses, etc., concerned with Blue Cross (including its early history) -- much of it separately classified by subject or by state.
  Material on state, industrial and cooperative medical plans, comprehensive group medical plans, and union health programs fills are also present, providing a mine of information about social trends of the period. This is material that cannot be duplicated and does not appear in any other library collection as a unit standing ready for the analyses of scholars of the future who will build on the experience detailed in the records of the Davis collection.
  - Cost of Medical Care, Subseries A
    - Medical Care Costs - Debts (Box 1)
    - Medical Care Costs - Expenditures (Box 1)
    - Medical Care Costs - Cost of Illness (Box 1)
    - Medical Care Costs - Cost of Hospitalized Illness (Box 1)
    - Medical Care Costs - Cost of Surgical Care (Box 1)
    - Medical Care Costs - Public Financing (Box 1)
    - Medical Care Costs - NY World Telegram Medical Care Costs Series (Box 1)
    - Health and Economic Status (Box 1)
  - Committe on the Costs of Medical Care, Subseries B
    - Schedules - used for various investigations by Committee (Box 1)
    - Pamphlets (Box 2)
    - CCMC - Records (Box 2)
  - Ability to Pay, Subseries C
    - Pamphlets and Articles (Box 2)
  - Income and Expenditures in US, Subseries D
    - Income Data (Box 2)
    - Reports and Pamphlets (Box 2)
  - Social Security, Subseries E
    - Advisory Council on Social Security (Box 3)
    - Citizens Conference on Social Legislation, 1954 (Box 3)
    - Citizens Conference on Social Security, 1953 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Economic Security (President's Committee, 1934-1936) (Box 3)
    - Social Security (except for Health Insurance) - General (Box 3)
    - Social Security Developments in Foreign Countries (Box 3)
  - Health Insurance, Subseries F
    - Health Insurance - General (Box 4)
  - Listings and Descriptions of Certain Health Insurance Plans, Subseries G
    - "Prepayment Medical Care Organizations" Klem, Social Security Board, Bureau Memo. 55 (Box 5)
    - "Directories of Non-Profit Service Plans" AHA, 1949, 1942, 1945 (Box 5)
    - "Medical Service Plans" and "Voluntary Prepayment Medical Care Plans" AMA, 1943, 1947, 1948 (Box 5)
    - "New Plans of Medical Service" Julius Rosenwald Fund, 1936 (Box 5)
    - Study of Civic Medical Center of Chicago, Illinois (Box 5)
    - List of Independent Plans, 1955-1962 (Box 5)
  - Bibliography on Health Insurance, Subseries H
    - Bibliography on Health Insurance (Box 5)
  - Dean Clark Report - Health Insurance Plans, Subseries I
    - Dean Clark Report - Health Insurance Plans (Box 5)
  - Blue Cross - Blue Shield, Subseries J
    - Blue Shield (Box 5)
    - Blue Cross (Box 5-6)
  - Medical Societies, Subseries K
    - Medical Societies vs. Panel Plans (Box 7)
    - California Physicians Service (Box 7)
    - Various State Medical Society Prepayment Plans (Box 7)
  - Insurance Companies, Subseries L
    - Commercial Insurance - General (Box 7)
    - Insurance Companies - Health Insurance Plans (Box 7)
    - Various Pamphlets re: Commercial Insurance Companies (Box 7)
    - Major Medical Insurance - (Catastrophic) (Box 7)
  - Industrial Insurance, Subseries M
    - Industrial Health Insurance Plans - General (Box 7)
    - Material on Specific Industrial Health Insurance Plans (Box 7)
  - Cooperatives, Subseries N
    - Cooperatives - General (Box 8)
    - Medical Rights Conference, St. Paul, Minnesota, 2/20/54 (Box 8)
    - 1st Regional Health Conference on Cooperative Health Plans - Two Harbors, Mich., 5/20/53 (Box 8)
    - National Conference on Cooperative Health Plans - Two Harbords, Mich., 8/1946 (Box 8)
    - Cooperative Federation of America - General and Newsletters (Box 8)
    - Group Health Association of America - General (Box 8)
  - Comprehensive Health Insurance Prepayment Plans, Subseries O
    - Comprehensive Health Insurance - General, Pamphlets and Articles (Box 8)
    - Group Health Association, Washington D.C. (Box 8)
    - Group Health Cooperative, N.Y.C. (now defunct), 1941 (Box 8)
    - Group Health Cooperative of Puget Sounds, Portland, Oregon (Box 8)
    - Group Health Insurance, New York City (Box 8)
    - Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York (HIP) (Box 8)
  - Labor - General Data on Health Insurance Plans, Subseries P
    - Labor's Attitude Towards Health Insurance (Box 9)
    - A.F.L., 1937-1943 (Box 9)
    - A.F.L. re: Health Insurance (Also Social Security) (Box 9)
    - C.I.O. re: Health Insurance (Also Social Security) (Box 9)
    - AFL-CIO Resolutions re: Health and Welfare (Box 9)
    - Labor Health and Welfare Plans, 1950- (Box 9)
    - Pamphlets on Health and Benefits in Collective Bargaining Agreements (Box 9)
    - "Directory of Prepayment Medical Care Service Plans: Open to Participation by Organized Labor Groups" Cooperative Health Federation of America and Committee for the Nation's Health (excluding Blue Cross, Blue Shield), 1954 (Box 9)
    - Health Insurance Plans for Workers and their Families (Box 9)
    - Health and Welfare Plans for Workers and their Families (Box 9)
    - Health and Welfare Plans Evaluated (Box 9)
    - Health and Welfare Fund Investigation (Box 9)
    - California Health and Welfare Plans (Box 9)
    - New York State Health and Welfare Plans (Box 9)
    - Labor and Medical Care for the Aged (Box 9)
    - Labor and Anti-Poverty Program (Box 9)
    - Labor and Federated Fund-Raising (Box 9)
  - National Health Insurance - Pamphlets and Articles, Subseries Q
    - Costs of Health Insurance (Box 9)
    - ISF Allocation Formula (Box 9)
    - Articles (Box 10-11)
    - NHI Pamphlets (Box 11)
  - Health Security Through National Health Program, Subseries R
    - Health Program Conference, 1944 (Box 12)
    - Health Program Conference Report (Box 12)
    - Opinion Poll (Peters-Boss Group), 1944 (Box 12)
    - Pamphlets of Controversy and Debate (Box 12)
    - Report (Box 12)
  - Medical Sociology, Subseries S
    - Medical Sociology (Box 12-13)
- Medical Care in the United States, Series 2
  Divided into sixty one sub-series.
  In this series, confidential reports made for foundations in the United States on the subject of medical care abound, and the files are replete with correspondence, publications, clippings, and other documentation on the distribution of medical care, medical care for dependents of military personnel, home care, and social medicine.
  Material contained in the file drawer on various diseases is of secondary sources, and although there are some scarce and unusual reports (e.g. The Middle Atlantic Educational Congress on Vision in the Defense Industry, April 1942 - a 218-page transcript), the bulk of this subseries is probably duplicated by the Academy's holdings. Apparently Dr. Davis used these materials for background information.
  When we go on to national affairs and social planning, however, we return to a principal interest of Dr. Davis', and again we come onto a number of usual documents - published and unpublished - such as increasing literate study that Benjamin C. Gruenberg made for the Committee on American Museum of Hygiene of the American Public Health Association in 1937, A Museum of Health.
  And so it goes, on and on, conveying early antipoverty programs, population problems, regional and medical programs for heart disease, cancer, and stroke, urban renewal and urban planning, health conditions in the United States, etc., with a great deal of material on the problems of youth in urban communities. The administration of medical research comes into its own throughout the records of these files, and there is a great deal of valuable material, much of it wholly ephemeral and not retained elsewhere, on various special, typical, and particular public or private health surveys. The file on Health in Wartime provides a specialsource on health programs in defense migration, the effect of war (usually referring to World War II) on the medical profession, the war and medical manpower, hospital and health center requirements in defense areas, etc.
  This series also contains material of an historical nature on rural economic conditions from the 1930's through the 1950s, and on rural health problems and programs, especially with regard to national and state government interest in health security measures for farm and migrating laborers. The section continues with extensive material in the nature of private reports, correspondence, surveys, and publications on group practice of medicine, including files on specific organizations, and on prepayment plans made by specific labor unions, much of it not available elsewhere.
  The series also includes materials on medical education (federal aid, intern training, regional cooperation, etc.), medical personnel, and physicians (choice and change of doctors, discrimination in medicine, the involvement of druggists, ethics, fee-splitting, etc.), specialists, dentists and dentistry, medical social workers, nurses and nursing, etc.
  Reports, correspondence, and publications on hospitals, including some complete and broken files of newsletters and reports of hospital councils and organizations, as well as privately conducted surveys and studies of hospitals, their services, administration, and financing are also present. Dr. Davis' files include an accumulation of years concerning the American Hospital Association and its various subsidiary parts, much of which is supplemented in the extensive separate correspondence files that make up a part of this gigantic collection.
  There is a large file on public medical care programs, particularly as they concern the aged and aging, public welfare programs, public health, and workmen's compensation (with detailed studies of variations, laws, etc.).
  Of special interest is a drawer devoted to some of the restricted records of the 1952 hearings of The President's Commission on the Health Needs of the Nation and other related confidential transcripts, correspondence, etc. There is a very complete file on the Salk Vaccine debate of 1955 which, besides containing hearings and releases from the U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare and from the Committee for the Nation's Health, has Dr. Davis' comments (manuscript lecture notes, correspondence, etc.), on all aspects of the argument. Also included is a valuable collection of different organizations' official and unofficial statements on the subject.
  Problems of Veterans Administration medical care programs and a small file on the War Stabilization Board Report on Health, Welfare, and Pension programs are housed in a large file drawer, three quarters of which is taken up by an extensive record related to Medicare, which bridges a break in Dr. Davis' collection between Series II and Series III, covering federal and state legislation for public health care under Social Security programs and other forms of state-administrated medical care.
  - Medical Care
    - General (Box 14)
    - Administrative (Box 14)
    - Comprehensive (Box 14)
    - Conference on Medical Care, 1944 (Box 14)
    - Diagnostic Services (Box 14)
    - Distribution on Medical Care (Box 14)
    - Government in Medicine (Box 14)
    - Health Services for Government Employees (Box 14)
    - History (Box 14)
    - Home Care Programs (Box 14)
    - Home Care vs. Office Care (Box 14)
    - Medical Care for Dependents of Military Personnel, 1953 (Box 14)
    - Medical Social Service (Box 14)
    - Multiphasic Screening (Box 14)
    - Needs, Industry Policy Statements (Box 14)
    - Nursing Homes (Box 14)
    - Preventive (Box 14)
    - Programs (see also Public Health, Programs) (Box 14)
    - Quality of Medical Care (Box 14)
    - Rehabilitation (Box 14)
    - Surgical Care Received (Box 14)
    - World Health (Box 14)
  - Social Medicine
    - Articles and Pamphlets (Box 14)
  - Trends in Medical Practice
    - Articles and Pampphlets (Box 14)
  - Various Diseases
    - Alcoholism (Box 14)
    - Cancer (Box 14)
    - Communicable Diseases (see also Public Health, Epidemiology) (Box 14)
    - Diabetes (Box 14)
    - Heart Disease (Box 14)
    - Mental Illness (see also Mental Health and Mental Health Centers (Box 14)
    - Pneumonia (Box 14)
    - Polio (Box 14)
    - Rheumatism and Arthritis (Box 15)
    - Tuberculosis (Box 15)
    - Venereal Disease (Box 15)
    - Vision (Box 15)
    - Various (Box 15)
  - Vital Statistics
    - Reports and Studies (Box 15-16)
    - Birth and Death Rates (Box 16)
    - Causes of Death (Box 16)
    - Infant Mortality (Box 16)
    - Maternal Mortality (Box 16)
  - National Affairs
    - Anti-Poverty Program (Box 16)
    - Automation (Box 16)
    - Brookings Institution and Health Insurance Study (Box 16)
    - Catholic Church and Social Problems (Box 16)
    - Congress (Box 16)
    - Harness - Committee, Articles and Speeches (Box 16)
    - Hoover Commission - Articles, 1948-1949 (Box 16)
    - Joint Economic Report, 1951 (Box 16)
    - Intergroup Relations, 2nd National Conference, 1948 (Box 16)
    - Labor - General Pamphlets (Box 16)
    - National Health Assembly (Box 16)
    - National Security (includes Civil Defense) (Box 17)
    - Population (Box 17)
    - Public Education System (Box 17)
    - Regional Medical Programs for Heart Disease, Cancer, and Stroke (Box 17)
    - Urban Renewal and Urban Planning (Box 17)
  - Social Planning and Problems -- Various Pamphlets and Reports
    - Various Pamphlets and Reports (Box 17)
  - Health Conditions in the United States
    - Adolescents (Box 17)
    - General (Box 17)
    - General Publicity on Health (Box 17)
    - Changing Patterns of Disease (Box 17)
    - Child Health, 1940-1948 (Box 17)
    - Child Health Services Study - Academy of Pediatrics (Box 18)
    - Chronic Illness - (Prolonged Illness, Long-term Patient) (Box 18)
    - Colleges - Health In (Box 18)
    - Comparative Health Factors among the States (Box 18)
    - Disability (Box 18)
    - Environment and Health (Box 18)
    - Eskimos (Box 18)
    - Genetic Factors (Box 18)
    - Handicapped (Box 18)
    - Health Hazards (Box 18)
    - Health Needs - General (Box 18)
    - Indians (Box 18)
    - Indigent (Box 19)
    - Industrial Health (Box 19)
    - Industrial Medicine (Box 19)
    - Injury Rates by Industry (Box 19)
    - Mental Health (Box 19)
    - Mental Retardation (Box 19)
    - Negro Health (Box 19)
    - Negroes (Committee for the Nation's Health Publications (Box 19)
    - Nutrition (Box 19)
    - Occupational Health Problems (Box 19)
    - Physical Fitness (Box 20)
    - Radiation and Health (Box 20)
    - Smoking and Health (Box 20)
    - Urban Youth (Box 20)
  - Medical Research
    - General (Box 20)
    - Federal Support of Medical Research (Box 20)
    - Philosophical Relations of Science (Box 20)
    - Research in Medical Care - Various Pamphlets (Box 20)
  - Health Surveys
    - General (Box 20)
    - National Family Survery of Medical Cost and V.H.I., 1955 (Box 20)
    - National Opinion Research Center Survey Forum (Box 20)
    - National Health Forum, 1955 (Box 20)
    - Illness Surveys - Various Pamphlets (Box 20)
    - Medical Care and Personal Care Requirements, 1944 (Box 20)
    - National Health Conference (1 and 2), 1938 (Box 20)
    - National Health Survey, 1935-1936 (Box 20)
    - New York City Health Department, 1963 (Box 20)
  - Health in Wartime
    - Civil and National Defense (Box 20-21)
    - Medicine in Time of War (Box 21)
    - Shortage of Doctors (in Wartime), 1943 (Box 21)
    - War Areas: U.S. Public Health Service Studies and Memos (Box 21)
    - Pamphlets and Reports Re: Wartime Health (Box 21)
  - Postwar Planning for Health and Security
    - General Pamphlets, Reports and Articles (Box 21)
  - Rural Conditions
    - Correspondence and MMD with Rural Sociologists, 1949-1950 (Box 21)
    - The Plight of Agricultural Labor (Box 21)
    - Cooperstown Conference on Rural Medicine, 1938 (Box 21)
  - Rural Economic Conditions
    - General, Folders I and II (Box 21)
    - Migratory Workers (Box 21)
    - Social Security (Box 21)
    - Rural Studies - Special Areas (Box 21)
  - Rural Health Conditions - General
    - Rural Health and N.H.I. (Box 21)
    - Rural Health Insurance Plans (Box 21)
    - Rural Health - General (Box 21)
    - Rural Action for Health (Box 21)
    - Rural Health and the A.M.A. (Box 22)
    - Rural Health Cooperatives (Box 22)
    - Rural Hospital Services (Box 22)
    - Rural Hospitals, 1936 (Box 22)
    - Rural Medical Care (Box 22)
    - Rural Infant Care (Box 22)
    - Pamphlets (Box 22)
    - Personnel - Resources (Box 22)
    - Survey and Plans of Special Areas (Box 22)
  - Farm Security Administration
    - FSA General (Box 23)
    - FSA Pamphlets (Box 23)
    - FSA Agricultural Workers Program (Box 23)
    - FSA Low Income Framers Medical Program (Box 23)
  - Group Practice
    - Articles - General, 1941-1948 (Box 23)
    - Articles - Medical Economics (Box 23)
    - Bibliography (Box 23)
    - Council of Group Practice (Box 23)
    - Dental Group Practice - Folder filed under Dentists (Box 23)
    - Diagnostic Centers (Box 23)
    - Group Practice - Legal Aspects (Box 23)
    - Group Medical Center - Architecture and Organizations (Box 23)